[Music]
This program is brought to you by
Stanford University. Please visit us at
stanford.edu. That's one d one not it's
not one definition of momentum. It's one
example of momentum and it's the one
that most people are familiar with. All
right. Now you go to lrangeian mechanics
and you remember that the lranjian of a
particle moving in
space has a term which is the mass times
the velocity squared over
two. And you notice that the momentum is
the derivative of the lranian with
respect to the
velocity that happens to equal the
momentum the same momentum. But now we
have some new concept of momentum namely
the derivative of
lrangeian with respect to the time
derivative of a particular coordinate
let's call it q
dot. Now if that coordinate happens not
to be the linear position of a particle
the position of a particle in cartisian
coordinates then it may well be that
this object is not mass times velocity.
An example would be angular momentum for
example where uh if we have a particle
moving in space and it has a term in the
lrangeian which for example could be m /
2 * r 2 time the angular velocity
squared. Then there's a a momentum which
you would get by differentiating the
lrangeian with respect to theta dot and
that's I'm sorry m
uh m r² yes m r 2 theta dot and that
would be angular momentum. It's not
linear
momentum. Okay. So anytime you have a
system which is described by a
lrangeian and in that lrangeian appears
time derivatives of variables you have
now a generalized notion of uh of
momentum which is the derivative of
lrangian with respect to the
corresponding velocity and that's called
also called
[Music]
p you could call it you could give it a
name you could call it p
subq Meaning to say the momentum that's
gotten by differentiating lrangeian with
respect to the velocity associated with
a coordinate Q. But that's a mouthful.
So we just call it the Q momentum. Or
better yet the momentum conjugate to Q.
Or better yet the momentum canonically
conjugate to Q. It's getting long. It's
getting as bad as the original thing.
Yeah. That definition for canotically
conjugate momentum appears to be
asymmetrical with respect to time and
that there's
no momentum that's canotonically
conjugate with respect to time just the
spatial coordinates.
So is that true?
Yes and no. Um there is a very useful
sense in which yeah what you're saying
is right. Of course, time in mechanics
is dealt with differently than space or
at least in in mechanics. In mechanics,
spatial position are the degrees of
freedom of the system. Time is the
independent parameter
uh that uh that just unfolds so to speak
and everything depends on time uh
through parametric dependence.
Now it wouldn't make any sense to
differentiate the
lrangeian with respect to the time
derivative of the time. What on earth
does that mean? It doesn't mean
anything. The derivative of the time
deriv the the derivative of time with
respect to time is just one. So it
doesn't make any sense at all.
However, when you're looking at
conservation laws,
uh, a simple example would be a
particle. We we did this last time. In
fact, we talked about two particles
interacting by a spring. But just to
remind you, if you have a langrian, for
example, mx do 2 / 2, which happens to
have a symmetry. This is a third
definition now of momentum. First one is
just m* v. Second one is partial of L
with respect to Q
dot. Now the third one which is not
really usually called moment well it is
for
um it's not considered a definition of
momentum. It's a theorem about conserved
quantities. Conserved quantities include
things like momentum. So momentum is a
special case of a conserved quantity
under certain conditions. What is the
conditions under which momentum is a
conserved quantity? It's the condition
that the lrangeian not change if you
shift the
coordinate by amount epsilon. If you
shift the coordinate x dot doesn't
change. And using ner's theorem which we
talked about last time you can prove
that mx dot is conserved. Basically it's
just a lranian equation that d by dt of
mx dot is equal to
zero. All right. So momentum is a
special case of a conserved quantity
which is conserved by virtue of a
symmetry. So that's another uh aspect of
momentum. Another aspect conserved
sometimes by
virtue of a
symmetry. Sometimes these are the same
things, sometimes they're not. Sometimes
they're the same concept, sometimes
there are not. For example, there are
systems where the lrangeian involves
velocities in a more complicated way. In
particular, a particle moving in a
magnetic field has another term that
also depends on velocity where the
momentum is in fact not mv. Anybody know
what the lrangeian is for a particle
moving in a magnetic field?
Right? There's another term, the vector
potential. Let's
uh the vector potential which is a
vector field plus the vector potential
dotted into the
velocity with the electric charge here.
All right. So for example, if I wanted
to calculate the momentum canonically
conjugate to x, I would want to
differentiate the
lrangeian with respect to x dot. What
does that give? It gives mx
dot and then from here there's another
term. This here is a subx x x dot plus a
suby y dot plus a subz dot and so forth.
And so there's another term which is
plus the electric charge times the
vector potential.
So there's an example where perfectly
ordinary momentum is not m well it's not
so perfectly ordinary but where the
momentum conjugate to a cartisian
coordinate is not mass times velocity
it's mass times velocity plus vector
potential. So the so at some so these
can diverge they don't necessarily have
to be the same definition here they may
be different.
Furthermore, it's quite possible that
momentum for a given system is not
conserved. So these really are three
different concepts which sometimes
converge and sometimes really define the
same object. Okay. Now what we studied
we took a field theory last time. Let's
forget that it had anything to do with a
string vibrating. And it was just a lr
it was just a field theory in which the
lrangeian density now I'll use scriptl
means lrange density the lrangege
density is
equal let me write the
lrangeian the lrangeian is the integral
over
space dx if there's three dimensions of
space this becomes d cubed x with three
dimensions of space and then we wrote
something with a 5 do^2 /
2 minus some
derivatives. Let's say d by
dx 5 sub
x^2 over 2 whatever
else. Now just like we define canonical
momentum conjugate to a coordinate by
the different by the derivative of the
lrangeian with respect to the velocity
we can define a thing called field
momentum.
Field momentum is not linear momentum.
It's not a vector in space. It doesn't
have a sense of uh of direction.
Ordinary momentum has a direction in
space. It's a
vector. So of course is the velocity.
Field momentum is not a
vector. It's a scalar. In fact, it's a
scalar with respect to rotations.
But its definition is just the
derivative of lrangeian with respect to
fi
dot. That's the canonical momentum
conjugate to fi. So it's quite a
different concept. Has nothing to do
with translation
symmetry. Has nothing to do with spatial
translation symmetry. It has only to
do with the field
phi. Okay. So what is that? What is that
canonical momentum? It's usually called
pi or often called
pi. Pi is like p except uh we're using
Greek letters now instead of Latin
letters. Pi is equal to the derivative
of the lrange density with respect to
phi
dot right? So it's field
momentum should not be confused with the
kind of momentum which when it hits you
knocks you in some direction.
All right.
Geometric. It's It is invariant under a
geometric rotation. Right. It's not
Loren invariant, but it is invariant
under a geometric rotation of
space. So, this would not be the kind of
momentum which when it hit you would
knock you in some direction. Has nothing
to do with uh with motion along some
axis. It has to do with motion in field
space if you like. Right? So that's
another concept of momentum.
Yes. Now last time you were going to uh
you did the first symmetry which you
added epsilon to yes five right and then
you're going to do you talked about
another symmetry where you displace
essentially x and uh does that also come
up with a conservation law? Yes, that's
what we're going to talk about now.
Good. in a moment. Let me just let me
just review though to to get back to
Yeah. All right. So, let me just remind
you of Nerther's theorem or the simple
slightly simplified version of Ner's
theorem that we uh that we've used. If
you'll have a symmetry and a symmetry
means an operation where you replace
each one of the Q's by
Q plus
epsilon time F subi of all of the
Q's. In other words, it's just a
transformation with a small parameter in
it. If the lrangeian doesn't
change, if the lrangeian does not change
or the lrangee density, let's just say
the lranian. If the total lrangeian
doesn't
change, if the total lrangian doesn't
change, then there is a conserved
quantity. And the conserved quantity is
the sum over all the
coordinates of the momentum conjugate to
the i
coordinate times f subi of q. In other
words, times this small shift. You can
neglect the epsilon there. Just f subi
of q. And that's the conserved. That's
the conserved quantity which is
conserved as a consequence of the
symmetry. Now in some cases as I said
let's forget this over here in some
cases it may correspond to one of the
other definitions of momentum. It may be
that the conserved sometimes this is
called a conserved charge for reasons
that will become clear. Uh but uh let's
just call it the conserved
um quantity. The conserved quantity may
be momentum. If this is
lrangeian then let's just go through it.
The delta x is just equal to epsilon
that means f is equal to one and the
conserved quantity is just
p just p momentum. So sometimes it can
be that the conserved quantity really is
momentum other times it may not
be right. So let's go back. Now this
lrangeian as it stands has a symmetry
and the symmetry is phi goes to phi plus
epsilon. Notice that this epsilon is
just a number epsilon. It does not
depend on where we're talking about.
It's not that ph of x is going to f ofx
plus epsilon of x. It's just f ofx going
to five plus a constant. Okay, a small
constant in this
case then we would say that f is equal
to
one and let's write out this nera
conserved quantity. It's that in this
case it becomes integral
dx. The integral dx replaces some on i p
subi is replaced by pi of
x. P sub
i. Well, first of all, sum on i is
integral dx. P subi becomes pi of x with
pi of x being written up here.
and f in this particular case is just
equal to
one. So this becomes our conserved
quantity the
integral which is equal to the integral
dx
of partial of ph with respect to
t. That's as long as there's nothing in
the problem which destroys the symmetry
of field translation.
Now I'll tell you some things that can
destroy the symmetry which would undo
this. Not undo it but I mean you know
undo it or reverse the uh the
conclusion. If there was another term in
here which was minus mui^ squar for
example we talked about such
terms then this
term is not invariant when you shift
phi. phi squar is most certainly not
invariant if you let phi change a little
bit and so that kind of term would
destroy the symmetry and it really
would.
Uh another
example is if we were talking about a
string or something like a string and
the string were pinned down at the end
points. Let's suppose we're talking
about translation of the string along
the vertical axis. Every point gets
moved
up. Well, that would be a symmetry. All
right, except for the fact that by
definition the end points are supposed
to be pinned
down. If the end points are supposed to
be pinned down, it's simply not a
possible operation in the system to move
all the uh all the points vertically
upward. And so the symmetry again is
destroyed. It's for this reason that you
can have let's let's look at a
particular motion. You can have standing
waves. Let's say standing waves which
you know go up oscillate up and
down. At this point over here all along
the string phi dot is positive. It goes
up to the top of its orbit up here and
the string comes to rest. So all the fi
dots become equal to zero. Evidently the
integral of phi dot is not
conserved. On the other hand, let me
imagine a string. Let me give you a
string connecting two points which does
have a conservation law. I think we
talked about this last time. Instead of
pinning the string down here, let's
imagine a pair of poles.
not poles in any mathematical sense, but
uh vertical
poles. And let's imagine that the rope
or the string was attached to these
poles by frictionless um rings which are
also free to slide up and
down. Then if the string is free to
slide up and
down, then it does mean something to
think about moving the string
vertically. Obviously the action or the
lrangeian doesn't change if you move the
whole string vertically upward. Uh the
derivatives that that's pretty clear and
so in that case the integral of phi dot
would be
conserved. So if you started the entire
string moving upward it would just
continue to go upward and upward and
upward. Wouldn't have standing waves
like that. It would uh
just levitate.
Okay, now let's come to some other I
want to I want to discuss well three
other conservation
laws. The first we've already discussed
again and it's just energy conservation
of
energy. This I'm not going to derive
again. It is a conservation law which
follows from a symmetry but it's a more
subtle symmetry. Go back to uh classical
mechanics. energy is conserved by virtue
of the symmetry where time goes to time
plus epsilon. Now, we're not going to
get into that tonight. We're going to go
back to our notes in classical mechanics
and remember how that worked. It's a
fairly involved little derivation. But
the point is that as long as the
lrangeian doesn't change when you shift
time, energy is concerned. It's almost
always almost always the case. uh that
the lrangeian is time
independent. It's time independent in
the sense that there's no explicit
dependence on time and in that case
energy is conserved. I'll remind you of
the formula for energy the general
formula for energy. If the lrangeian
I'll give you both a special case and
the general case. If the lrangeian of a
system happens to be of the form that it
contains velocities
squared q sub i dot
q subj dot now this is not really
squared just quadratic in
velocities. If it's quadratic in
velocities you can take the simple case
where it's the sum of velocities
squared. can contain coefficients,
masses or whatever you like. Let's just
simplify it and say it's some sum of
coefficients. I'll call them m subi over
2 * q subi dot squared. This does not
have to be uh linear motion. Just as
long as lrangeian contains quadratic
things like this, right? And also things
which don't depend on a velocity, we
usually call them the potential energy.
In other words, if it can be rewritten
as a kinetic energy minus a potential
energy, then it follows that the sum of
the potential energy and kinetic energy
is conserved. T plus
V T plus U T plus U is
conserved. And as I said, that uh
that is an example of Ner's theorem, but
a more involved one that I don't want to
go through again. it uh we traced it
through in mechanical. A quick question
about explicit dependence of time. Does
that some somehow imply an external
force or something? Yeah, it usually
implies some external force which is
varying with respect to time. That's
right. That's the sort of thing that it
involves. Right. For example, here's
here's an example. Supposing you have a
harmonic oscillator. Now if the harmonic
oscillator potential is fixed in other
words if the spring constant is fixed
with time independent of time then the
energy is conserved there the lrangeian
is then x do 2 m / 2 plus sorry minus k
/ 2 x^2 usual harmonic oscillator but
now let's change things a little bit
let's imagine let's see how can we
imagine the spring constant changing.
Can you imagine the spring constant
changing with
time? Yeah. Yeah. The spring constant
might depend on the temperature. The
temperature might vary with time. We
don't want to take into account all the
motion and the molecules and everything
else. So, we're going to summarize all
of this by just saying the spring
constant depends on time. Now, the
lrangeian has explicit time dependence.
If it has explicit time dependence like
that then energy is not conserved. Of
course what's happening is energy is
going from one form to another but the
mechanical
energy described just by this thing by
itself is not conserved. So if there's
any explicit time dependence in other
words if the parameters of the problem
spring constants masses other parameters
if they depend on time explicitly then
the energy is not conserved because as I
said that can that usually means that
we've ignored part of the system and
just treated it uh by uh by ignoring its
dynamics and just uh saying there was
some time dependence in the system.
Okay. And in connection with that, is it
the same thing to say that the partial
derivative of the langium with respect
to time the partial derivative the
partial derivative holding everything
else fixed meaning the fields and their
time derivatives. Yes. Right. So you've
got basically you've got q's q dots and
t and if and if the partial derivative
respective t absolutely that's what it
means. That's what it means. That's what
it means. Yeah. Yeah. Right.
Okay. Gold called Gold called Gold.
What's his name? Had said that. He He
said it the way you did, but he never
said who's he Gold. What's his name? The
mechanical. Oh, Goldstein. Goldstein.
Yeah.
Yeah. Well, you know, if Goldstein was
teaching this class, he probably would
have said it on the blackboard when you
asked the question.
Yeah.
Right. Right. What the hell does that
mean? Yeah. Um, good. All right. So,
let's write down then the expression for
the energy for the simple field theory.
Uh, let's not include let's not include
this um m 5^2
term. Let's just take the simple field
theory. It could have more dimensions.
I've written it as if space was just
one-dimensional.
Uh you can add in y and z if you like.
I'm not going to do it. It's too much
writing. Um yeah. What is the energy?
The energy total energy is then
m x dot uh sorry phi dot
squared. You have to integrate it over
space. 5 dot squared.
kinetic energy plus potential energy and
that means plus in this case fi so let's
see not m just f do
squared plus 5 subx^2 and if you like
plus 5 y^2 blah blah
blah in other words it's the sum of the
square of the time derivative and the
space derivatives that's the total
energy notice that it's always positive
or zero
uh and um let's in fact look at it.
Let's let's compute it. Let's take the
case of a waves of waves going in one
dimension. So our field now has some
profile and let's imagine a wave moving
in the positive xaxis.
That means it has some profile but its
full dependence is not just five of x
but five of x and t and it has the form
five of x minus
ct. Oh, are there some uh c's in
here?
Yeah, as it stands it's not
dimensionally consistent. This is a
derivative with respect to time. This is
a derivative with respect to space. So I
think we have to put a c squ here.
Uh C is space over time. Yeah, that's
right. We have to put a C ^ squ
here. Okay. Now, if we solve the
equations of motion, we find out that
there are solutions which just move
rigidly down the x-axis or up the
x-axis. Two kinds of solutions. Let's
take the right moving solution. There's
also a left moving solution where we
would change the sign of the sign to
change the sign of the uh CT term.
And let's calculate this phi dot^2 + c
^2 dy by the
x^2. Okay, this is
phi. Phi does not depend on x and t
separately. It depends on the
combination x minus ct. So what is phi
dot dy by
dt? That's the derivative of f with
respect to its argument. Shall we just
call that fprime? fprime means the
derivative of f with respect to what's
inside its argument
here times the derivative of the
argument with respect to
t that's minus c. So that's minus
[Music]
c minus c *
frime. That's the derivative of five
with respect to t. And the derivative of
phi with respect to
x that's just
fprime. Differentiation with respect to
x just gives fprime. Okay. So what is
the energy then? The energy is the
integral is
12. The
integral fi dot squared. That's c^2
fprime
squared. That's the first term. And then
the second term is another c ^2 frime
squ. In other words, just forget the
factor of
two
and get rid of one of
these. That's the total energy of a wave
moving to the
right. Integral dx. What about a wave
moving to the left? Well, the difference
for a wave moving to the left, here's a
wave moving to the
left, that would change the sign
here, but it would not change the sign
of the square of d5 by dt
^2. So once again, it would be exactly
the same expression. 1/2, let me remind
you what it was.
12 the sum of two
terms one of which was c^2 frime 2 over2
and the other of which was c^2 frime 2
over2 all right same
thing the square of phi is not going to
change the square of phi dot is not
going to change so this term won't
change it'll be exactly the same and so
the energy of a left moving wave and a
right moving wave are the same that's
not surprising of course uh and in In
fact, it wouldn't change if I rotated
the wave into some other direction if I
were doing it in three
dimensions. The profile of the wave
counts, but not which direction it's
moving in. So, let's just write this
out. That's that's the
energy. Good. Any questions about energy
conservation? Yes.
Cing the speed of light. Oh, yeah. Yeah.
It's the speed of light. Sorry. So
yeah theory well the speed of the speed
of propagation
speed propagation is not equal to speed
no it's um no you see if the no okay
let's let's talk about that supposing
this was sound all right you would put
in there the speed of sound okay would
that make sound loren variant well it
would be true that The sound waves the
soundwave theory would be invariant
under certain transformations but they
would be the Lorent transformations with
the wrong speed of
light. Okay. Okay. So you say so what
it's invariant with respect to Lorren
transformations with the wrong speed of
light. But then there would be other
things for example the mechanical motion
of particles or other waves which might
h might be described by a lorenvariant
theory with the right speed of light.
The combined things together would not
uh would not be Loren variant in the
usual
sense. So
oh they all have the same speed of light
right
miracle. And one one has a perfect right
to ask why is that so? But it's well you
even have a right to ask how do I know
that? Okay, we know it well one way the
way we know it is because these things
tend to influence each other. Uh the
Higs field affects the electron motion
affects the uh photon in various ways
and they all get mixed up together in a
rather serious way. If there was any
violation of Lorenson variance, it would
infect its way through the rest of uh
the rest of the physics and we would
know about it unless it was extremely
minute. Unless the unless the violation
of Loren variance was extremely minute.
So for example, just take electrons and
photons. The maximum speed of an
electron is believed to be exactly the
same as the speed of light. Believed to
be exactly the same. uh therefore they
both both sets of objects photons and uh
and electrons are invariant under the
same Lorren
transformation. Okay, what if the
maximum speed of electrons were slightly
different than the maximum speed of
photons or if the speed of gravitons
were a little bit different than the
speed of
photons? Okay. uh then the physics would
not have an exact loren variance because
the two pieces of the physics would have
different loren variances and the
combined system together wouldn't have a
single loren variance.
Um, as long as electrons interact with
photons, those are going to get
themselves mixed up in a way that uh
that they're going to affect each other.
And we would know about it from very
very high
precision quantum electronamics
experiments and so forth unless that
velocity difference was sufficiently
small that numerically we couldn't uh
distinguish.
Yeah. If you were moving the opposite
direction to a sound wave, the sound
wave relative to you would still asmtote
at C. Right? So in that sense, no, no,
no, no, no, no. If you were moving
relative to a soundwave, you will see
that sound wave move with a different
velocity than the speed of light than
the speed of sound. Right? That's what I
mean. And it will increase. But as to
see asmtote with respect to what? When
you say something asmmptotes, you have
to say asmmptotes with respect to some
something. No, no, no, no. Asmtotes with
respect to some process. I mean, with
respect to some uh the division of
velocities
um Oh. Oh, sorry. Wait. There are two
C's in this problem now. There's the
speed of sound and there's the speed of
light. Let's call the speed of sound. Uh
yes. So, I'm saying the speed as the
speed of light. Oh. Oh. Oh. Okay. So,
yeah. You're sayinging a sound. Good.
You're saying supposing a sound wave was
going down the x- axis and relative to
to you it's moving uh with what a
thousand uh is it a thousand feet a
second or something something like that
moving a thousand feet a second but
there I am zipping down the axis with
very very close to the speed of light
then I would see the sound wave moving
very close to the speed of light that's
right yeah and in that sense it's and
that's Well,
uh, in that sense, but I don't think
that's worth too much, frankly. Yeah.
Um, okay. So, that's the energy c ^2 *
frime
2. Next, I want to come to the concept
of linear momentum. Linear momentum for
fields. Now, this is not a momentum
which is conjugate to the field. This is
actually the stuff which if it hit a
particle, it would make the particle
move off along some axis. In particular,
it's a momentum which will be different
for waves going to the left from the
right. In fact, for waves going to the
right, the momentum will point that way,
the linear momentum will point that way.
And for waves going to the left, the
linear momentum points the other
direction.
So what
and this is part of the ordinary
momentum but it's part of the ordinary
momentum which is carried by waves in
quantum mechanics. It becomes the
ordinary momentum carried by photons for
example. All right. So it's the ordinary
momentum as carried by the waves. What
does it have to do with? Well, ordinary
momentum has to do with translation
invariance. So we can
ask is this lranian here invariant under
translation spatial
translation and if so what is the
conserved quantity and this is a little
bit subtle it's a little bit abstract
but I'm going to run you through it and
I'm going to work out for you what the
conserved quantity that we identify with
translation invariance is. Okay, let's
imagine that we take a
wave. Let's say that it's f ofx. We
don't need to worry about its time
dependence right now. It's got some
profile five ofx. And we take the whole
wave and we move it a little bit. We
rigidly move it.
If you take a look at that
lrangeian, it's quite obvious that the
integrated lrangeian won't change. All
I've done is I've displaced everything
uniformly and that should not change the
total amount of kinetic energy or the
total amount of potential energy. It may
change the kinetic energy at each point,
but all you're doing is substituting
this point over here for this point over
here. the can after the wave has been
displaced a little bit. Uh if I do
displace it, if I imagine displacing it,
then anything that was originally going
on over here, exactly the same thing is
now going on over here. Anything that
was going on over here is now going on
over here. So when I add up all the
terms in the kinetic and potential
energy, then after I shift the wave a
little bit, they will be the same
kinetic and potential energy. Not the
kinetic energy the same as the potential
but the kinetic energy before and
after. All right. So how
then does ph ofx change when I displace
the field a little
bit? It does change if I stand at a
particular point. If I'm the eye in the
sky over here looking at that point and
I shift the wave. This is not an upside
down a. It's an eyeball.
and I'm staring right at the field where
I'm where I am and I shift the wave a
little bit. The field
changes. So this shift of the field is
associated with a small change in phi.
How much does phi change if I shift the
field to the right a little bit? What's
the change in phi? That's right. The
change in
phi if I shift the field to the right a
little
bit. derivative of five with respect to
x times delta x. Now is it plus or minus
that? This is the hardest thing in the
world to figure
out. Uh
okay, let's check. Supposing
fi you think it's minus. I
think I also think it's minus but I'm
not sure why. Uh going you're moving
backwards.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. I think it's
minus d5 dx times delta x,
right? It's either one or the
other. It's the rate at which phi is
changing times the amount that you shift
by. Okay. So that's the change in
phi. At every point in space, phi
changes by amount this much.
Well, that's an example. It's a special
case of this idea that delta Q, the
change in a Q is epsilon times a
function of all the
Q's. In this case, epsilon is just
epsilon, but f of
q is the partial of with respect to x.
That's what
represents f of q, the small
displacement or the small change in pi
when I do the
operation. Now we can very easily
calculate the conserved quantity.
Remember what the rule is for the
conserved quantity. I erased it off the
blackboard, but it's just to take
pi, multiply it by
f, and integrate over space.
That's the same as sum of p
subi times f subi of
q. So we take f of q, we multiply it by
the canonical momentum and we integrate
it over all space and that gives us a
quantity. Let's just call that quantity
I don't know what to call it. Let me
call it
p. P because in fact it really is a
certain
momentum. All right. What is it? It's
given
by d5 by dx. I guess it's minus d5 by
dx times
pi pi
subx integrated over all space.
That's the momentum which is conserved
by virtue of the invariance of the
lrangeian with respect to spatial
translation. That's a mouthful. The
quantity which is conserved by virtue of
translation
invariance. Okay. What is
pix? Where do we have it? Pix is just
phi dot.
So for our special case this is just
minus the
integral of d5 by
dx time dy by
dt that quantity is conserved as I said
by virtue of translation invariance
let's suppose that our system that we
were talking about was a combination of
particles and waves
electromagnetic radiation and
electrically charged
particles.
Supposing I displace all of the waves,
all the electromagnetic waves by
distance epsilon, but I don't displace
the charged particles. Do you expect the
dynamics to be invariant under that
translation? No. No. In fact, if I
displace the radiation so that it moves
away from the charged particles, that
obviously changes things, changes
energies and so forth. But supposing I
displace the waves and the charged
particles
together. Then I do expect that the
lrangeian not change. So in such a
situation I would expect that the total
momentum would have a contribution
coming from it from terms having to do
with the electrons and terms having to
do with the waves. What would be the
part of the momentum that would just
correspond to the electrons themselves?
MV. MV for each
electron. What would be conserved? the
thing that would be conserved would be
the field momentum plus the ordinary
momentum of the uh of the charged
particles. So this thing actually
deserves to be called the ordinary
momentum associated with the field
itself.
In fact, roughly what we prove by this
line of argument is that if this field
were to interact with a collection of
ordinary particles and bump them, push
them and do whatever it does to them
that the momentum of the particles plus
the field would be conserved if the
lrangeian is invariant under a total
shift of everything
simultaneously. That's why this is
called the it's not called the ordinary
momentum. Then it's called the momentum.
But which momentum? Let's call it the
ordinary linear momentum.
Okay, let's calculate it for our right
moving wave. Now, it's quite possible
that I've got the sign wrong here. We
will find out if I got the sign wrong
because any fool can see, including me,
that a wave that's moving to the right
should have a positive momentum and a
wave moving to the left should have a
negative momentum. So, if I've got the
sign wrong, we'll find
out. We'll find out because our right
moving wave moving down the positive
x-axis will wind up having negative
momentum, negative uh momentum along the
x axis. That's a bad thing. So, we'll
change the sign, but let's do it. Okay,
let's
uh here we are again. Dy by dt is c * f
prime.
Ah, let's Yeah, we want this is the left
mover.
We want I want the right mover and then
there's a minus sign here,
right? Yeah. Now we have a right mover.
And what do we have then? We have dy by
dx * d5 by dt. And that looks to me like
the linear momentum is the integral
dx of minus looks like I got it right.
minus d5 by dt * d5 by dx. That gives me
a factor of c. Another minus
sign and fprime
squared. Fortunately, I seem to have
gotten the sign right. And the linear
momentum of the of the right moving wave
is positive. Notice that it's closely
related to the energy of the right
moving wave. In fact, apart from a
factor of C, the energy and the momentum
are equal to each
other. Right? We can write that this is
equal to C *
P. There's an extra factor of C in the
energy that's not there in the
momentum. What about a wave moving to
the left?
That's like
this. That changes the sign of this one,
makes it
plus and changes the sign of the
momentum since the momentum has a
natural minus sign in
it. P in that case becomes minus
this. So a wave moving to the left, the
momentum is exactly the same except that
it's moving in the opposite direction.
Well, it's exactly the same except that
it's exactly opposite.
uh in
sign. It's not hard to work out the more
general case where a wave may be moving
in an arbitrary direction. And of course
the answer is that momentum is a vector.
This kind of momentum is a vector and it
points along the direction of motion of
the wave. But these are two uh simple uh
situations.
So we can then write for these kind of
waves that energy and momentum are
related. Let's write down the general
relationship. Momentum is a
vector. P is a
vector and the
energy a spatial vector an ordinary
three vector. Energy is a spatial scalar
and energy is equal to C times the
magnitude of the momentum.
You know any particles that have this
property that their energy is equal to C
times their momentum?
Photons. Photons. Photons. In fact, any
particle that moves with the speed of
light has the property that its energy
is equal to its momentum time C or the
absolute value magnitude of its momentum
time C. So, we've discovered another
conservation law, the conservation of
linear momentum. And the formula for it
doesn't involve fi uh fi dot squar and
fx^ squar but involves a product of fx
and fi d5 by dx and d5 by
dt. Okay.
Um yeah. Um if I was in two dimensions
and I had a wave that was um symmetrical
about the origin, does it have zero
momentum? Yeah. Yeah. Even though it's
carrying energy.
Yep. You're thinking about a spherical
wave or a circular wave. Somebody
somebody makes a puddle uh you know a
wave going out and ripples. Zero total
momentum but it does not have zero
momentum
density. I have not talked about the
concept of energy density and momentum
density. We will we need to talk about
that. This is a good example good
reason.
Um uh but yes it has it has overall
total
zero momentum even though it has zero
even though it has non zero energy. Okay
let's take a fivem minute break and I'm
going to take a fivem minute break. I'll
be back in a few
minutes. Okay let's talk about another
conserved quantity. Now this conserved
quantity is associated with a particular
kind of field. A field whose field
variable is complex.
Now a complex field of complex in the
sense of complex
numbers a complex number
Z is just a real part plus I * an
imaginary
part or we could call it Z1 + I
Z2. So every complex number is just a
pair of real numbers but you deal with
it in a certain way by certain rules.
uh the complex conjugate of
Z is equal to Z1 minus I Z2 or X minus I
Y.
Uh let me just write down some simple
facts about complex numbers to just
remind you
star complex
conjugate. What else do we need to know?
uh zstar
z is just x^2 + y^2 or z1 2 + z2 2 and
finally every complex number can also be
written as a magnitude r
* e to the i theta where theta is an
angle between 0 and 2 pi. It
represents the the position of the
complex
number x y or it can also be written in
terms of r and
theta. r e to the i theta. Oh, last
thing z
star is r e to the minus i theta. All
right, that's that's uh that's your
course in complex numbers. Now
um a complex field and on one level can
be just thought of as a pair of real
fields just for some reason there are
two fields in our problem. They're very
similar to each other. They have very
similar properties and we just call them
fi 1 and fi 2 or we group them
together and possibly just for some
notational
convenience we write that phi is equal
to 51 +
i2. We also write that phi
star is equal to fi 1 minus i2.
Uh the derivative of phi with respect to
any
coordinate is equal to the derivative of
51 with respect to x mu plus i times the
derivative of fi 2 with respect to x mu.
Incidentally one and two here do not
mean derivatives.
They just mean real and imag I I think I
might have done better to call it fi
real plus I fi imaginary but I've
already committed myself fi 1 plus i
fi2. So I'm not using the subscript
notation now to indicate
derivatives. All right so the real and
imaginary part of derivatives are just
the derivatives of the real and
imaginary part and so forth. It's all
very simple. Now let's write a lrangeian
for this pair of fields. The two fields
are very similar to each other. Each one
has the same kind of lrangeian that
we've written before.
Namely
L equals integral
D3X or I might have just written Lrange
density but let's write it down.
51 dot meaning time derivative squared
over two plus derivatives with respect
to spatial position of
phi squar /
2 sub
1 x y z all of them can go in here and I
might even for fun add in plus mu / 2
51^ 2 I might also add in many other
things but oh sorry minus I think we're
we got some minus signs here
huh minus
signs all right everybody recognize that
for fi
1 just the same kind of lrangeian we've
written down in the past I've added in
this mu term the so-called mass
term all right that's for one now what
about for field number 2 that also
enters into the lrangeian. Same thing 52
dot^2 / 2 minus dx 5
2^ 2 /
2. Add in y and z derivatives if you
like. But let's also add in minus mu
over two. Same mu by 2 ^
2. I can use the complex notation to
simplify this. First of all, let's
concentrate on this 51 2 and 52 2. 5 1 2
+ 52 2 is the same as five
star. That's just five
star. What about 5 1 dot squar + 52 dot
squared? That's fi 1 dot. That's fi dot
* 5 star dot. A 1 2 plus a 2^ 2 always
means a thing times its complex
conjugate.
So all of this can be simplified into
the form integral
dx 5 dot star * 5 dot /
2. This stands for fi 1 dot^ 2 + 52 dot^
2. Likewise for the spatial derivatives,
dx fi star
*
dxi /
2. And finally, minus
mu / 2
star. This lranian of course has all of
the symmetries that we've discussed so
far.
Well, it doesn't have the shifts. It has
some of the symmetries. In particular,
it has energy conservation. It has
momentum conservation. But it has a new
symmetry. A new symmetry and a new
conserved quantity. One that plays a
very major major role in particle
physics and quantum mechanics, but we're
studying it at the level of classical
physics at the moment. Anybody know what
that symmetry is?
Yeah. Right. Exactly. Let's take
phi and multiply it by e to the i
epsilon. epsilon is any complex any real
number.
Now any real number what does that do in
terms of the co you know if we if we
plot phi on the uh cartisian axes in
terms of a real and imaginary part it
just takes fi and rotates it a little
bit. It rotates the angle
um it rotates the angle theta theta a
little
bit. So it rotates phi in this
direction. It rotates five star in the
other direction.
This
is a particular operation that we can do
on
phi.
Okay, epsilon I'm imagining for the
moment that epsilon is very small. Let's
imagine epsilon is very small. We don't
have to but I want to make contact with
the idea of a small transformation
involving a small parameter epsilon. If
epsilon is small, what is e to the i
epsilon? It's 1 + i
epsilon. 1 + i epsilon if epsilon is
small plus things higher order in
epsilon. That's just the formula that e
to the x is equal to 1 + x + x^2 over 2
factorial plus x cubed over 3 factorial
blah blah blah blah blah. If I terminate
this after the first term for very small
values of x then e to the x is 1 plus x
e to e to the i epsilon is 1 + i
epsilon. So for small epsilon what we're
doing is multiplying
phi by 1 + i epsilon. Now is that a
symmetry? Is the lrangeian changed if I
multiply phi by e to the ippsilon? And
here it's obvious that it doesn't
change. Five star phi does not get
changed when I multiply phi by e to the
ippsilon. The e to the ippsilons cancel
when you multiply five *
5ar. And so five times five
star or anything five time five dot time
five star dot
uh you know what I meant five star dot *
fi
dot any of these expressions involving a
star time an unstarred thing will not
change if you just multiply phi by e to
the ippilon because it changes.
Say it again.
Eus. Ah exactly when phi if you multiply
phi by e to the
ippepsilon then you must multiply phi
star by e to the minus
ippepsilon.
So if you change phi by an amount e to
the plus i epsilon you change five star
by a factor e to the minus ippepsilon.
In other words, you can write that the
change in
phi under this kind of transformation is
I epsilon *
5. Right? What is the change in five
star? It's minus i epsilon * 5 star.
Does everybody see where I got this
from? I just said the change in phi is I
epsilon * fi. That's the little change
here. And if I do the same thing for
five star, I find out that it changes by
with a negative thing over
here.
Okay. Is this a symmetry? Yes, it is a
symmetry. The langian does not change
because it always involves things like
five * 5 star. Is there a conserved
quantity associated with it? Yes, there
is. I'll show you the little
manipulation. You can go home and work
it out without using complex notation.
I'm going to use complex notation. I'm
going to do a slight cheat on you, but
you can go home and check what I've done
by using the actual real components of
fi in the lrangeian. But here's the
here's the here's the trick.
There are two independent components of
phi. I'm going to pretend that the two
independent components of phi are fi and
phi
star. You can check that this will
actually work and give you the right
answer. So here's the idea. What is the
canonical
momentum conjugate to phi? The canonical
momentum. Oh, let's Oh, let's Yeah, here
it is. Here's our lrangeian.
What's the canonical momentum conjugate
to phi? It's the derivative of the
lrangeian with respect to fi dot. Right?
That's its definition. But that's just
five star
dot. So this is five star
dot. What's the canonical momentum
conjugate to five star? That's the
derivative of lranian with respect to
five star dot. That's fi
dot. Pi conjugate to five star is equal
to
five
dot over two. No. No. Um, yeah, I guess
there is an over two. Yeah, you're
right. There is an over
two. I missed that. Yep, there is an
over
two. It won't affect the value of the
conserved quantity. Now these two
expressions are
shorthands for the momentum conjugate to
fi 1 is fi 1 dot and the momentum
conjugate to fi2 is fi2 dot. There's
short hands for that and uh they really
just uh represent that. Notice that the
canonical momentum conjugate to phi star
is the complex conjugate of the
canonical momentum conjugate of phi.
They're complex conjugates of each other
pi and pi uh pi
star. Okay. Now let's work
out
the conserved quantity. the conserved
quantity we know what the change in phi
is remember what
uh in other words we can say f
subi is i * fi and f subi star is minus
i * star remember what f is everybody
remember what f
is the small change in phi except for
the factor epsilon
on same
f as in ner's
theorem. Now it's straightforward to
work out. I'm going to work this out for
you another way. I'm using a fancy
notation the complex notation for
something which uh which we'll do
another way. Let's just let's do do it
this way. Uh what's the conserved
quantity? It's pi
subi
times
fubi pi subi f
subi plus pi subi star time f subi star.
Now what have I left
out? Integral over
space that's the summation over i. The
analog of the summation over I is the
integral over
space. Let's see what it
is. Pi
subi is five star dot over two. So this
is here equal to did I leave an i out
somewhere? No, I didn't.
Five star
dot /
two times f_subi and f_subi is i
* that's one term. Now the second term
pi subi star that's five dot over
two. And
now f sub 5 star but that's minus i
* 5 star. So there's a minus
i * 5
star. That's the most untransparent and
least obvious expression I think I've
ever written down on this blackboard for
you. Five star dot * 5 minus 5 dot * 5
star
integrated over
space. Let me just derive it another way
which doesn't make use of this fancy
complex notation.
Let's write fi is equal to fi 1 + i fi
2. And now again I'm going to multiply.
Let's see what happens to fi 1 and fi2
under this transformation. Let's just do
it. 51 + i2 gets
multiplied times e to the i epsilon
which is 1 + i
epsilon. And this is equal to fi
1 plus or minus excuse
me min
[Music]
51 plus
i2 plus i epsilon * fi 1 +
i2. All I've done is multiply it
out. What's the change in fi 1? Well, f1
is by definition the real part of this
expression. The change in the real part,
let's look at it. There's a real part
from here. The real part of Ipsilon *
this thing here is minus epsilon * fi 2.
I * i is min -1 epsilon * 2. And then
there is plus i epsilon
1.
51. Here's the rule. The change in fi
1 is equal
to minus epsilon 52 and the change in fi
2 is equal to epsilon * fi 1.
Now you just go through Ner's theorem
using this form for the changes of fi 1
and fi 2 and you'll find exactly the
same expression for uh for the conserved
quantity written in terms of the real
and imaginary part. I'll I'll leave you
to do that. Substitute in the real and
imaginary parts and just work out what
the right answer is. But this formula is
quite neat. 51 star * 5 minus 51 star
dot * 5 minus 5 dot time five I'm losing
it it's getting late five star do five
minus five dot five star
okay anybody know what this conserved
quantity corresponds to in physics
angular momentum well it is a it is a
kind of angular momentum but it's not
angular momentum
It first of all doesn't have an axis
associated with it. What axis would you
be talking
about? No axis. It contains only space.
Sorry, it contains only time
derivatives. So it has no vetorial sense
to it. Angular momentum is a
vector. So it can't be that.
Yeah. Electric
charge. Electric charge of what?
electric charge of the field. That's
right. Now, where are we going? We're
going slowly creeping up on ideas of
quantum field theory. Remember
that when we
finally get
to think about the relationship between
particles and fields that every field
has associated with it field
quanta. Every kind of particle is a
quantum of some
field. So
photons are quant of the electromagnetic
field. Now they are not in any useful
sense complex fields. The electro the
vector the electromagnetic field is
real. The electron is also the quantum
of a field. It's not a field that you're
used to thinking about. It's not a field
that you measure easily in the
laboratory with a field detector.
But electrons have fields associated
with them. They are the quanta of a
field. They're not fields which exert
forces on electrons. They are the fields
whose quanta themselves are the
electrons. They're fields which are made
up of flowing electrons if you like. Uh
other particles in nature uh quirks.
Quirks are also charged particles and
they also uh are described by fields.
meaning to say that uh that they are the
quant fields. Charged particles are
always described by complex
fields. Complex
fields. This is the expression for
the electric charge carried by such a
field. It's an integrated thing which
means that the thing in the brackets
here is a kind of charge density. If
this is the thing that you integrate
over space to find the total charge,
then the thing in the bracket here must
in fact be the density of
charge. You integrate a charge density
over space to find the total charge.
This must be it. So this expression in
here actually stands for charge density.
And if you think of the field and its
relationship to a collection of a large
number of
particles, then this is just a field
description of the average charge
density of the particles that make up
the field. Now, this really hits home
only really when we get to uh when we
get to quantum field theory where the
relationship between particles and
fields becomes more manifest. But for
the moment you can simply imagine that a
field moving along has an electric
charge. What happens if this field
interacts with the electromagnetic
field? Well, the electromagnetic field
may collide with this field and scatter
it much as if this were a collection of
charged particles being influenced by
the electromagnetic field.
uh the motion of wave packets of this
field might follow trajectories which
are similar to the charged particle
trajectories in an electromagnetic
field.
So we're not getting deeply into quantum
field theory at this point. But this is
a conserved quantity which
is when we move on to quantum mechanics
and the quantum field theory does become
the electric charge of the quanta
described by the field five. You want to
give a name to the inagram? Charge
density. Charge density. Charge density.
Right now somebody Do they describe
electro electromagnetic fields? No, they
don't describe electromagnetic fields.
They describe the electric charges which
are sources of those fields and which
are acted on by those
fields. They're not electromagnetic
fields. They're not electric and
magnetic fields. this
fi they
are the fields whose quanta are
electrons
this is sort of classical except for
except for the fact that you have the
complex field so no that's classical
that doesn't make it non-class right
okay well then if you is there is there
an example where you can plug that in to
show how that comes out charged like the
yes yes but in order to see that we
would have to couple to the
electromagnetic field and I'll tell you
how to do that
eventually. All right. So this is
lrangeian by itself which is not yet
coupled to the electromagnetic field. So
it's a system of charged particles but
with no uh no electromagnetic field
around. All right. We will have to
change this lrangeian a little bit when
it comes in contact with the
electromagnetic field. And then the sort
of thing we would like to see for
example is that a wave packet of this uh
you know if we had a wave packet which
took like this moving down the axis in
this direction and it encountered an
electric field in this direction we
would like to see that what it does is
to bend the uh the trajectory of the
wave
packet in the same way that an
electromagnetic field
would. So obviously we have to do more
work to see that at the moment this is
just a conserved quantity. This is a
conserved quantity. But why did I do it?
I did it because ultimately it become uh
electric charge and not just electric
charge. Uh many many different
quantities in physics electric charge
isotopic spin all the various different
conserved quantities that are associated
with particles.
uh color charge, um
strangeness, all of those uh various
quantities are described by complex
fields like this or things very similar
to this. Can you can you do uh the same
or similar thing with two real fields
and a rotation? Yeah, that's what this
is. That's exactly what Oh, sorry. Um
where where did I write it? when I wrote
it in terms of fi 1 and fi2 which I seem
to have erased somewhere that was
exactly the rotation properties of two
real fields you could get the same oh
absolutely yeah it is the same yeah now
let me give you another perspective on
it which might be helpful I don't know
might not be helpful but let's come back
to the
string so we have the string connected
between two points but now I want you to
imagine that the string is vibrating not
just in the vertical direction but also
the horizontal direction. So if we
projected it onto a
plane at any point the string would be a
uh the string would intersect the plane
at a
point. Okay. Now that means that the
actual configuration of the string is
described by two fields. One of which
can be thought of
as the y component and the other could
be thought of as a z component or we
could just call them fi 1 and fi
2. The two components of the position
anywhere's along
here. The string intersects here's the
origin. The string intersects the plane
at some point and it describes it can be
described by a complex field phi which
could be fi 1 plus i2 or fi yeah 51 plus
i2. So if we had a string which was free
to move in two directions x and y we
could describe it either by two two real
fields. one describing the x position of
the field along the along the string,
the other describing the y position. Or
we could describe it by a single complex
field, a point on the complex
plane. What uh would you guess that for
the string, for the string, for the
mechanical analogy, what would you guess
that this corresponds to? Anybody got an
idea?
Somebody actually said the word
before, however, in a in a different
context. It's the angular momentum of
the string, but the angular momentum of
the string as
it the angular momentum of the string
about this axis. In other words, this
string, if you if you focused on a point
on the string, it would be moving. It
would be moving back and forth in
various ways. At any given instant, it
might have an angular momentum about
this
axis. This is nothing but the angular
momentum of that string about the
longitudinal
axis.
So, here's an example. Here's a when you
say this, you mean the whole integral.
Yeah, the whole integral the whole
integral sums up the angular momentum of
each point along the string. Right? So
and the angular momentum density would
be this. Now this is not this this is in
the anal in the um in the analogy in the
analogy of field is like string is like
violin
string electric charge is like angular
momentum in the plane in which the
string is
moving. Okay. So for example, a possible
motion of such a
string. Possible motion could be a
standing wave oscillating up and down or
a standing wave oscillating in and out.
But there are also oscillating waves
which just uh circulate around like
this. You take the you take this bent
string, you give it a velocity into the
blackboard and what does it do? It uh it
um jump rope. Rope skipping. Rope
skipping. Rope skipping. Yeah, that's
the analogy. Rope skipping. When uh the
children uh play rope skipping, they're
giving the rope an angular momentum
about the axis uh defined by the
distance between the two children.
that angular momentum is a natural
analog of electric charge for this uh
system here for the uh for the system of
a string. We're not getting yet into
quantum field theory but do you know
what do you know about angular momentum
in quantum
mechanics? It's
quantized happens to be quantized in
units of h bar but especially it's
quantized. It comes in discrete
multiples of something. What do you know
about electric
charge? It comes in discrete multiples
of the electric charge of the
electron. Uh is it a
coincidence? Well, maybe it's a
coincidence, but it has a common
description in terms of uh fields of
similar description. Yeah, there's not
counting quarks if we count. Yeah, I
mean, right. Quarks count everything.
Count all charged particles. But uh
Quarks don't come in discrete multiples
of the charge of the electron.
You're right. Discrete multiples of the
charge of a quark.
Can you actually You're right. Put this
in. But that that's a subtle business
that uh
that is a truly subtle business. The
fractional charge of quirks. So I'll ask
you to forget about it for the moment,
but maybe we'll get a chance to come
back to it.
Uh can is there an example where you
just have say instead of a string and an
actual electric field that can be
expressed as the complex and you could
you could take an electric field of a
charge sorry the not the electric field
you could take the electric field
associated with electromagnetic wave
electromagnetic wave going down the
z-axis has an x component and a y
component e x plus i ey.
You could, that is to say, you could
make a complex electric
field ex plus
i call that a uh and then a circularly
polarized wave would have this aspect of
being like the jump rope. All right? In
that case, it wouldn't be electric
charge. It would be genuine angular
momentum of the field because it really
corresponds to a spatial
uh uh spatial direction.
It really corresponds to rotation of
real space, not rotation of this
fictitious space. So what's the simplest
example where you can clearly show that
it's a
charge that's being conserved?
No, I said you have to you have to study
the connection between this and the
electromagnetic field and then you can
show it. They have to be two separate
fields together. You have to take the
electromagnetic field, which means the
vector
potential, and couple it in the
appropriate way to this, and then show
that a wave packet of this stuff will
move as if it were a charged particle in
the electromagnetic wave. And then that
that's that's feasible. We might even
get to do it, but uh not tonight.
Right
here.
So are we saying that the conserved
quantity is imaginary? No.
This is the complex conjugate of this.
What happens if you take the difference
of two comp of two things a thing and
its complex conjugate
hary?
Yeah. So the difference between this and
this is pure imaginary and when it
multiplies this it's pure real. Good.
That's a good point. If this were plus
then we'd start to worry about it. But
it's minus which means that this
quantity inside the bracket is
imaginary. Oh, in fact you get rid of
the i over two. So that is just the real
part. Yeah the real that's right you
know that's what I thought because you
were almost there with the uh you had
already written that uh pi star or you
didn't write but you mentioned that pi
pi star
uh is the complex conjugate of pi. Yeah.
Okay. And you also have actually uh f
star is the complex conjugate conjugate
fv. Yeah. And so you already have uh
integral dx pi
v plus pi vfv star. Yeah. And that's
already right the real part. Let me show
you one more thing.
If we were talking about the
string, then the fi's themselves would
become the coordinate position x and y
of the string. What would the fi dots
be?
Velocities. This would be the
crossroduct of the position and the
velocity which is called the angular
momentum. x * vy minus y * vx is exactly
what this would be. So the mathematical
structure of this thing is very much the
analog of the mathematics of the
rotation in an extra couple of
dimensions. It's not totally surprising
that particle physicists are always
interested in extra dimensions.
Yeah, we talk about the electromagnetic
field and the gravitational field, but
then you come and you say the field
whose quanta are
electrons. Is there a common name for
that field? And a common
name, a quantum field.
Every there's a every type every
particle type is associated with a
field. Every field type is associated
with a particle.
and associated with the same connection
that connects photons to the
electromagnetic field. The
electromagnetic field comes in discrete
quant of
energy called
photons. Those photons are particles.
They can be isolated one at a time. They
can be sent through
slits. Uh they make clicks when they hit
the photo detectors and they behave like
particles when they're sparse enough.
In the same way charged particles
uh well in the in the opposite way
charged particles can be grouped
together to form something which is
similar to a
field and those fields
uh come in discrete packets of energy
that describe
particles. If it's a charged particle it
must be described by a field which is
capable of describing that charge. So
the field has to have a conserved
quantity associated with it and in the
sort of coarse grain you can roughly
speaking you think you can think of the
field as a sort of coarse grained
description of the charges. The coar
grain description of the uh of the
charge is just this quantity composed
out of the field. So there's probably 50
elementary particles. So there's 1500
fields too.
Well, presumably you could have a proton
field too, right? What could you have a
proton field? So it's not elementary
particle, right?
About non-charged particles. Well, the
proton field would be a construct that
you would build out of quark
fields.
Uh but yes, you would have a proton
field. the molec molecular fields,
fields for describing molecules, fields
that describe bowling balls. It's just
not a very useful concept for bowling
balls. It's hard to build a kind of
coherent simultaneous motion of a lot of
bowling balls at
the but in principle.
Yes, you were somebody was going to ask
a question about the relationship of
charged particles to electric fields.
What about particles that don't have a
charge? Say it again. Particles that
don't have a charge, neutral particles,
they do they relate to electric field as
well. Do they what? Do they connect the
same way a charged particle would
to charge particles? Uncharged particles
are also described by fields, but those
fields don't interact with the
electromagnetic field.
At the moment, we haven't described the
connection between these charge carrying
fields and the electric and magnetic
fields. They're different animals. They
have different symbols. Electric field
is E. Magnetic field is B. This is
neither of
them. This quantity that's in the
bracket here, what would you call that
in
electronamics? Row.
standing for what? For charge density.
Um, how about current? Can you guess?
Can you make a guess? If this is the
electric charge
density, what would does anybody would
anybody like to venture a guess?
No, no, no. It can't that's a that's not
a bad guess. But the reason it can't be
right is it's got to have a direction of
space associated with it. Current flows
in a direction. Current is a vector.
No, road dot doesn't have a sense of
direction. Road dot is connected with
the current. It's the divergence of the
current. But uh
h derivative of momentum.
It's very simple. Let me rewrite this.
This is a charge density. It's
derivative with respect to t of
phi star * phi and then minus another
term with an
i/ x
y z. In other words, derivative of I
times the derivative with respect to X
I. I could be X, Y, or Z time 5
star. That's a thing now that has a
vector index. This has a direction in
space. It could be derivative with
respect to X, could be derivative with
respect to Y, could be derivative with
respect to Z. When you combine it with
derivative with respect to T, you get
four components.
The four components form a four vector.
That four vector is composed out of the
electric charge density and the electric
charge flow. The the usual electric
charge um uh
current. So a very similar kind of thing
except not with time derivatives but
space derivatives forms the electric
charge
um current. We haven't gotten to it, but
uh but uh we will get to
it. Any other
questions?
But we got a few minutes.
Um what would the u uh in the example of
the uh of the wire, what would the uh uh
the uh conserve quantity be for current
flow for J?
for a wire.
Well,
oh, you mean for the uh sorry for the
Yeah. Yeah.
Um
Oh, the wire you mean the uh the jump
rope? Jump rope. Yeah. Just exactly
this. This would be the flow of charge
along the
x-axis or the flow of angular momentum
along the x-axis. There is a notion of
of angular momentum density which can be
just identified more or less as the
angular momentum of each particle in the
jump rope. But now if you have a wave
going down the axis. Imagine imagine
okay so we have uh we have a rope and we
start twirling it like this. Waves go
down the axis but they're sort of
circularly polarized waves. In that case
there's a flux of angular momentum.
Angular momentum is traveling down the
string.
And that traveling angular momentum is
the analog of the uh of the electric
charge um
current, right? Of course, it's a
different thing. I mean, it you don't
have to take a wire and spin it in order
to make electric charge go down it, but
you have to spin it in this internal
space, this uh this fake space of pi 1
and pi 2. Yeah.
So this gives you some idea if nothing
else about why uh as I said why particle
physicists uh do have an interest in
internal
dimensions that the quantum numbers the
conserved quantities that are associated
with particles often in fact always can
be can be considered motions in hidden
spaces.
Now the hidden spaces may be purely
mathematical or they may even be hidden
spaces but one way or another the
mathematics of these conserved
quantities is very closely related to
the mathematics of motion in extra
spaces and in particular angular
momentum type quantities in extra spaces
extra dimensions of space.
So that's where we may ultimately get to
maybe
what what would uh uh what would be your
uh your symmetry transformation to get J
to get no no J is not a conserved
quantity. It's the integral of row which
is the conserved quantity.
J is a flux of a conserved quantity.
So for example, let's see and here's a
sense in which J is not a conserved
quantity. You can
have a flow of charge down an axis
here. Okay. Some other kind of
object, a photon coming here scatters
these particles and turns them around
and turns their direction around. J
turns around. J goes from being positive
to being negative. So J is not
conserved. But the total amount of
charge is
conserved. that there's one km of charge
here going to the right becomes one kumm
of charge going to the left. The um the
uh the char the charge flow the current
is itself not conserved. So every every
conserved quantity typically has a flow
associated with it. You drain a battery
charge is conserved but the current you
drain a battery the charge is conserved
but the current certainly is not the
constant. Right. Right.
Right? Current itself is not conserved
charges. But it's generally the the case
that conserved quantities have connected
with them a flow of the conserved
quantity. So total amount of water is
conserved. Uh the flow of water is not
conserved but there is a flow that's
connected with the conserved quantity
itself. That's
uh and we haven't discussed that
connection except to say that the
say the field whose quant electrons it
has a fi1 and fi 2. Mhm. Do the fi 1 and
52 have any physical meaning that we can
think of? Not not really.
Um no more than uh saying out of it you
can build these conserved quantities.
Uh perhaps if we were a zillion zillion
times smaller, we would see these extra
dimensions and see things moving around
in them and say, "Oh, electric charge.
Oh, that's just the angular momentum of
something spinning in some one of the 10
dimensions of string theory or
something." Uh but from our perspective,
what we get to see out of the whole
thing is the electric charge and that's
about all. We don't get to see the
internal motions that uh that might be
connected with it. We're too big.
Equation the rate of change plus the
divergence of a conserved quantity is
always zero or something. Yeah. Good. So
that's what we're going to do next time.
But uh if you want to jump ahead of the
game a little
bit, that's called the continuity
equation. Continuity equation is that
the time
derivative of the density of charge plus
the space derivatives in just one
dimension. This is derivatives partial
derivative plus the space derivative of
the uh charge flow the
current is equal to
zero. That's of course a statement.
Well, I'll tell you what it's a
statement of next time. And we want to
check that. We want to check that that
that's a true statement. Uh that the
that the really behaves that way.
I I thought
of d row
dt since row is conserved isn't no the
integral of row is conserved. The
integral of row is conserved. Right? So
what I'll tell you what this equation
says. It says that if you have a region
of space with some charge in it, the
only way that the charge can change in
that region is by a current flowing into
or out of the
region. So it says that you can't have a
change in charge unless you have a
current to carry that. You can't have a
change of charge in a region unless uh
unless there's a flow of charge out of
that region or into that region. So it's
the connection between the flow and the
change of charge in a given
region. And of course what this says is
that if there's a change of charge on
the inside of this region then there's a
compensating change of charge on the
outside of the
region. So it's a uh it's a kind of very
local way of describing the conservation
of charge. For example, what's not
allowed is for charge
You might think that conservation of
charge would allow the following charge
to disappear over here and at the same
instant that it disappears over here to
reappear over here. That would that
would uh still satisfy the rules of
conservation of charge. Total charge
doesn't change. But that's not the way
things work. The way they work is that
charge gets from here to here by flowing
through the region in between. so that
you can detect the fact the charge is
flowing from here to here by stationing
yourself over here with a current
detector and discovering the charges
move through here. So conservation is
more
than just saying a quantity doesn't
change. It says that when it does change
you can account for that change by a
flow or a flux of the quantity through
the boundaries of a region. And we're
going to take that up. Yeah. Is there an
experiment in physics that shows that
that happens? Oh, I'm sure there is. I'm
sure there's a zillion uh you know,
yeah, sure. I mean,
uh I can I think of an experiment off
here? No, but just think about what it
means. It means that if you have a
wire and the charges move from one from
the charges just move along the wire,
electrons move a little bit to the left.
What happens? Let's take that case.
electrons in the wire all move to the
right. What happens to the wire? What
happens to the wire is some minus charge
shows up over here. Some plus charge
shows up over here. Why? All the
electrons have moved to the
right. Each electron has moved to the
right a little bit. Each one has moved
to the right by the same amount. There's
no buildup of charge in the interior,
but there's an increase of charge,
negative charge over here because some e
some one extra electron showed up here.
One extra electron disappeared from
here. So what you get is a net charge on
the ends of the wire. That net charge on
the ends of the
wire happens all right happens every
time you put the wire in an electric
field or something. But if you were to
stand there and monitor what's going on,
you would see a flow of charge across
there. You wouldn't just see charge
appear over here and disappear over
here. You would see them all marching to
the right. So yes, I'm Yes, there there
are uh for example, every time a charge
increases over here and decreases over
here, a magnetic
field due to the flow of charge in there
is produced.
What what I'm thinking of is quantum
tunneling where it suddenly appears on
the other side of the barrier. So that
means that it must have been in the
barrier at some time. It was in the
barrier, but there'll be a flow of
charge to go with it. You'll see a
sudden uh you had a detector in the
barrier. If you have a detector in the
barrier, it will detect that
charge. Right. You can't make the charge
go through the barrier. Uh if there is a
detector there, it will detect the
charge. Yeah. Would you say kind of
general it'll also screw up the
tunneling
but in kind of in general at least in in
classical theory that uh anytime you
have some kind of a global law that
essentially there are local processes
that are that it originates in. Yeah. Um
in fact I would say that for most global
laws at least global conservation laws
uh but most global laws altogether I I
can't think of any global laws except
global conservation laws but they tend
almost always to be associated with
local laws that uh that are as you
say not always there are
exceptions things called multiplicative
quantum numbers which are uh a little
different but uh okay so let's yeah if
you want to study something study the
continuity
equation d row dt plus dj dx
[Music]
the preceding program is copyrited by
Stanford University please visit us at
stanford.edu edu.